Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Project Records, 1936-1989; 1942-1962; Series IV
  - Job 4807: General Motors Technical Center, Warren, MI
    - Specifications for Styling Administration Building [FB]
      - Bulletins #51 - #71, 1954 (Box 148, Folder 393)
      - Bulletins #72 - #85, 1954-1955 (Box 148, Folder 394)
      - Bulletins #86 - #99, 1955 (Box 149, Folder 395)
      - Architectural, 1953 (Box 149, Folder 396)
      - Electrical wiring systems; elevators; electric stairways, 1953 (Box 149, Folder 397 - 398)
      - HVAC; kitchen equipment, 1953 (Box 149, Folder 399)
      - Steam fitting trades; plumbing; fire protection, 1953 (Box 149, Folder 400)
    - Specifications for Styling Studios and Shops Building [FC]
      - Building work, 1952-1953 (Box 149, Folder 401)
      - Bulletins #1 - #20, 1952-1954 (Box 150, Folder 402 - 403)
      - Bulletins #22 - #40 [missing #21, #33], 1953-1954 (Box 150, Folder 404)
      - Bulletins #41 - #60, 1954 (Box 150, Folder 405)
      - Bulletins #61 - #80, 1954 (Box 150, Folder 406)
      - Bulletins #81 - #97, 1954-1955 (Box 150, Folder 407)
      - Collector systems; electric stairways, 1952, 1954 (Box 151, Folder 408)
      - Electric freight elevators; hydraulic levelator; steam fitting trades, 1952-1953 (Box 151, Folder 409)
      - Fire protection; paint sprays; ovens, 1952 (Box 151, Folder 410)
      - Heating, ventilating and air conditioning, 1952-1953 (Box 151, Folder 411)
      - Kitchen equipment, 1952-1954 (Box 151, Folder 412)
      - Plumbing, 1952 (Box 151, Folder 413)
    - Specifications for Process Development Administration Building [GA]
      - Building work, 1952-1953 (Box 151, Folder 414 - 415)
      - Bulletins #1 - #20, 1952-1953 (Box 151, Folder 416)
      - Bulletins #21 - #38, 1953-1954 (Box 152, Folder 417)
      - Bulletins #39 - #59 [missing #56], 1954 (Box 152, Folder 418)
      - Electrical wiring; electric passenger elevator, 1952 (Box 152, Folder 419)
      - Fire protection, 1952 (Box 152, Folder 420)
      - Heating, ventilating and air conditioning, 1952 (Box 152, Folder 421)
      - Plumbing; steam fitting trades, 1952 (Box 152, Folder 422)
    - Specifications for Process Development Shop and Foundry Building [GB]
      - Building work, 1952-1953 (Box 152, Folder 423 - 424)
      - Bulletins #1 - #18 [missing #5, #15], 1953 (Box 153, Folder 425)
      - Bulletins #19 - #31, 1953-1954 (Box 153, Folder 426)
      - Bulletins #32 - #52 [missing #49], 1954 (Box 153, Folder 427)
      - Electrical wiring, 1952-1953 (Box 153, Folder 428)
      - Heating, ventilating and air conditioning, 1952-1953 (Box 153, Folder 429)
      - Hydraulic freight elevator; cranes, 1952-1953 (Box 153, Folder 430)
      - Plumbing, 1952-1953 (Box 153, Folder 431)
      - Steam fitting trades; fire protection, 1952-1953 (Box 154, Folder 432)
  - Job 4811: Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, St. Louis, MO: Competition
    - Correspondence
      - Contract for preliminary investigations of winning design for presentation to Congress, and financial correspondence with associates, 1948-1951 (Box 154, Folder 433)
      - Preparation of presentation to Congress, 1948-1951 (Box 154, Folder 434)
  - Job 4901: Aspen Music Center, Aspen, CO
    The Goethe Bicentennial Convocation and Music Festival hired the firm of Saarinen and Saarinen, but Eero was largely responsible for the design of the Aspen Music Center, a fireproof canvas tent 147 feet long on its four sides and 45 feet high. The 2,000-person seating area was set into an eight-foot-deep depression dug out of a sloping site surrounded by mountains and formerly used as a cow pasture. Constructed at a modest cost of $15,000, the tent was connected by a covered walkway to a 23-by-100-foot wood-frame building housing dressing rooms and a storage area, where the disassembled tent could be stored in the off-season. The building was completed in 1949 and demolished in 1963. Smith, Hegner, and Moore were the project's associate architects; Bolt and Beranek, acoustical consultants; Stanley McCandless, lighting consultant; Herbert Bayer, color consultant; and Maurice Hoopingarner, general contractor. U.S. Tent and Awning Company manufactured the tent.
    - Clippings, 1949, 1962, undated (Box 154, Folder 435)
    - Drawings, undated (Box 155)
    - Photographs
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 154, Folder 436)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 154, Folder 437)
      - Models, undated (Box 154, Folder 438)
      - Negatives and transparencies, undated (Box 154, Folder 439)
    - Specifications: Progress report [containing tent, acoustical and lighting specifications], 1949 (Box 154, Folder 440)
  - Job 4903: Yale University, New Haven, CT: Campus Planning
    Yale president A. Whitney Griswold asked Eero Saarinen to assist the university in expanding its campus. Saarinen and his associate, Douglas Orr, worked on three areas: a sloping site (now called Science Hill) to the northeast of the main campus, the Payne Whitney Gymnasium vicinity, and Cross Campus. For Cross Campus, they proposed a freestanding administrative tower, on axis with the main entrance of the Sterling Memorial Library. The tower, with a square footprint, was to be placed on a plaza enclosed by four new low-rise buildings flanked by existing structures. Six buildings were to be demolished to make way for this group, which nonetheless retained the street walls that were characteristic of the Yale campus. They also proposed a rectangular, seven-story, flat-roofed administrative building opposite Woodbridge Hall, which housed the offices of the university president. The Physics Building, proposed for a site atop Science Hill, was the most developed of the three master plan projects.
    Job numbers for projects at Yale are scattered and relate to different periods of the project. Researchers are advised to thoroughly search Series IV of this collection for related material. Separate scope and content notes are provided for the David S. Ingalls Rink and Morse and Stiles Colleges, as the projects themselves are discrete. Series II, the Professional Papers, also contains a great deal of material pertaining to Saarinen's committee work at Yale. Please also see the A. Whitney Griswold papers at Manuscripts and Archives (RU #22) for correspondence between the University president and Saarinen regarding these commissions.
    - Clipping: "College Buildings: Campus Planning: The Unique World of the University", Eero Saarinen, Architectural Record, 1960 (Box 154, Folder 441)
    - Drawings
      - Existing conditions and proposed development, undated (Folder 687A)
      - Master plan, site studies, proposed buildings, undated (Box 156–157)
    - Photographs
      - Aerial photographs of existing site, undated (Box 675, Folder 79)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 154, Folder 442)
      - Site plans, renderings, 1948-1951 (Box 154, Folder 443)
    - Preliminary Master Plan for Yale University, presentation brochure, 1957 (Box 671, Folder 10)
  - Jobs 4905, 4901L, 5101, 5103: Brandeis University, Waltham, MA: Campus planning
    Shortly after Brandeis opened its doors in 1948 as the nation's first Jewish-sponsored, nonsectarian university, its president, Abram Sachar, and board of trustees selected Eero Saarinen and Associates to devise a master plan for a ninety-acre campus of rolling hills and wetlands outside Boston. Expected to be realized over ten years, the plan, developed by Saarinen and Matthew Nowicki, called for the demolition of approximately ten existing buildings on the site, saving only a castlelike structure that had formerly housed Middlesex Medical College.
    The university officially adopted Saarinen and Nowicki's plan, but Saarinen completed only seven structures: the five-building Ridgewood Quadrangle and two buildings in the Hamilton Quadrangle. The Ridgewood Quadrangle, a residential complex initially intended to house faculty and married students, is located on the periphery of the campus. Archie Riskin, a Boston-area architect, produced the working drawings, supervised construction, and was responsible for the selection of the building materials. The quadrangle was rushed to completion in 1950 to meet the demand for undergraduate student housing. A Boston-area firm, Richmond and Goldberg, served as associate architects; Hubbard, Lawless, and Blakely were the consulting engineers. Saarinen's other buildings for Brandeis were the Sherman Student Center and Shapiro Hall, both part of Hamilton Quadrangle. Both buildings were designed in collaboration with Richmond and Goldberg, though Riskin completed them. Hyde and Bobbio were the mechanical and electrical engineers, and Paul S. Calkins the structural engineer.
    Job numbers for projects at Brandeis overlap and relate to several different periods of the project. Researchers are advised to thoroughly search Series IV of this collection for related material. Jobs 4905, 4901L, 5101, and 5103 pertain to campus planning as well as to the Women's Dining Hall and Residence Hall (Job 5101) and the Dining Hall and Social Building/Student Center (Job 5103). Photographs documenting the projects and campus at Brandeis are extensive. The projects also contain four rolls of drawings across the job numbers, brochures for the master plan produced by Saarinen's firm and by the university, building specifications, and sketches.
    - Clippings, 1951, 1954 (Box 154, Folder 444)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1958-1960 (Box 154, Folder 445)
    - Photographs
      - Athletic fields renderings and sketch, undated (Box 154, Folder 446)
      - Auditorium and Shapiro Memorial Art Theatre: renderings, site plans, floor plans, section, undated (Box 154, Folder 447)
      - Campus models, undated (Box 154, Folder 448)
      - Chapels: renderings, sketches, site plans, undated (Box 154, Folder 449)
      - Dormitory renderings and sketches, undated (Box 154, Folder 450)
      - Existing site conditions, [1949?] (Box 154, Folder 451)
      - Gym and natatorium: renderings and sketches (Box 154, Folder 452)
      - "Heart of the Campus" renderings, undated (Box 158, Folder 453)
      - Humanities and Social Science Building sketches, undated (Box 158, Folder 454)
      - Library sketches, undated (Box 158, Folder 455)
      - Museum and Fine Arts School: renderings, plot plan, floor plans, undated (Box 158, Folder 456)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 158, Folder 457)
      - School of Medicine renderings, undated (Box 158, Folder 458)
      - Science Building: renderings, sketch, floor plans, section, 1951, undated (Box 158, Folder 459)
      - Site plans; aerial view renderings, undated (Box 158, Folder 460)
      - Student Union renderings and sketch, undated (Box 158, Folder 461)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 682, Folder 140)
    - Slides: graphics, undated (Box 158, Folder 462)
  - Job 5001: Irwin Union Bank and Trust Company, Columbus, IN
    This building was the first of three in Columbus designed by Eero Saarinen for the J. Irwin Miller family. The one-story square glass pavilion (with a basement) is set back from its property line on three sides, with the fourth side bordering a tree-studded parking lot and a driveway featuring an early example of a drive-through banking window. In front of the building's entrance facade on the town's main commercial thoroughfare, Washington Street, a row of sycamore trees helps maintain the street wall. Saarinen developed the bank's design after a trip to the Great Mosque in Cordoba, Spain, which, along with San Marco in Venice, he later cited as a design source. Every desk in the bank was equipped with chairs designed by Saarinen. Severud, Elstad, Krueger Associates were structural engineers on the project; Hyde and Bobbio, the mechanical and electrical engineers; Bolt, Beranek, and Newman, the acoustical consultants; Stanley McCandless, the lighting consultant; and Dan Kiley, the landscape architect.
    - Clippings, 1954-1957 (Box 158, Folder 463)
      - Additional material (Box 671, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1955-1962 (Box 158, Folder 464)
    - Drawings
      - Addition of Drive-In Tellers, undated (Box 159)
      - Architectural working drawings, tracings and bulletins, undated (Box 160)
      - Furniture layout and miscellaneous drawings, undated (Box 161)
      - Structural (tracing), mechanical, electrical (sepia) working drawings and bulletins, undated (Box 162)
    - Furnishings, signs, equipment, 1953-1954 (Box 158, Folder 467 - 469)
    - Photographs
      - Exteriors, 1955, undated (Box 158, Folder 468)
      - Interiors, 1955, undated (Box 163, Folder 469)
      - Renderings and models, 1955, undated (Box 163, Folder 470)
    - Public relations
      - Bank brochures, 1953, undated (Box 163, Folder 471)
      - Press releases; downtown tour information, 1954, 1981, undated (Box 163, Folder 472)
    - Slides: Model and exterior, undated (Box 163, Folder 473)
    - Specifications
      - Addenda and bulletins, 1953-1954 (Box 163, Folder 474)
      - Electrical; mechanical, 1953 (Box 163, Folder 475)
      - Food service equipment, 1953 (Box 163, Folder 476)
      - Furniture and equipment, 1954 (Box 163, Folder 477)
      - General conditions; elevators, 1953 (Box 163, Folder 478)
      - Planting, 1954 (Box 163, Folder 479)
      - Site development and drive-in tellers' booths, 1965 (Box 163, Folder 480)
  - Job 5004: Miller, J. Irwin Residence, Ontario, Canada
    Saarinen designed this summer cottage, on a long rocky peninsula on a lake, for the family of J. Irwin and Xenia Miller. Two one-story units were separated by a stone-paved terrace that was partially roofed by the house's second-floor space. The ground floor of one unit contained a two-level open-plan living room, with a built-in sofa and freestanding fireplace, and a master bedroom suite. The ground floor of the second unit housed a dining room and a kitchen with an eat-in area. The second floor contained five bedrooms and two bathrooms. The uninsulated house featured wood and stone walls inside and out. The limited amount of documentation for this project, which sustained a fire, includes two beautiful colored-pencil plans of the house.
    - Drawings: Sketches, undated (Box 680, Folder 129)
      - Floor plan sketch, color, undated (Folder 684B, Folder 160)
      - Additional floor plan sketch, color (Box 710)
    - Photographs
      - Negative, undated (Box 163, Folder 481)
      - Site plan; model; aerial view, 1953, undated (Box 163, Folder 482)
      - Snapshots; color image of fireplace, undated (Box 163, Folder 483)
    - Slides: Interiors, exteriors, views, Circa 1966 (Box 163, Folder 484)
  - Job 5005: Saarinen, Eero Guest House/Saarinen, Loja [Mrs. Eliel] Residence, Birmingham, Michigan
    - Drawings, undated (Box 164)
    - Photographs
      - Negatives, [1953] (Box 163, Folder 485)
      - Plans, [1953] (Box 163, Folder 486)
  - Job 5007: Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA: Kresge Auditorium
    The architect William Wurster, dean of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology's School of Architecture and Planning, invited Eero Saarinen and Associates to design an auditorium, a nondenominational chapel, a student union, and a plaza connecting the three buildings on a flat site across Massachusetts Avenue from the institute's domed classical building complex (1912-1938), which was designed by William Welles Bosworth.
    The Kresge Auditorium, designed with Anderson and Beckwith (Lawrence B. Anderson and Herbert L. Beckwith were professors at MIT), was the nation's first large-scale concrete-shell building. The structure constitutes one-eighth of a sphere, configured triangularly and placed on a red-brick podium. Inside, the raked seating of the column-free oak-paneled main auditorium accommodates 1,238 people. Below grade, another theater seated 200.
    The auditorium's curved ceiling presented acoustical problems; Saarinen, wanting the ceiling to remain exposed, worked with the acoustical engineers Bolt, Beranek, and Newman to design sound-enhancing white-painted panels that are suspended from above and improve the room's acoustics.
    Saarinen's other completed building for MIT, the 128-seat Kresge Chapel, is a windowless, flat-roofed cylinder fifty feet in diameter, clad in rough-surfaced brick and supported on brick arches springing from a twelve-foot-wide water-filled moat. A glazed rectangular passage bridging the moat forms the entrance to the chapel. Sculptor Theodore Roszak's spire incorporating a bell stands on the chapel's flat roof. Inside, a second undulating brick wall fits within the exterior shell and is separated from a low spandrel wall by a horizontal glass infill panel. Light also enters the chapel through an oculus directly above a white stone altar raised on a circular dais, producing ever-changing patterns on a curved screen designed by Harry Bertoia. This sculptural element is composed of many small metal rectangles attached to wires stretched between the floor and ceiling. Like the auditorium, the chapel was designed with Anderson and Beckwith. Bruce Adams of the Saarinen office was a principal collaborator on the project. It is also worth noting that Saarinen's memorial service in 1961 was held at the Chapel.
    A third building Saarinen designed for MIT -- a student union -- was not realized. This long narrow five-story structure was to have facades composed of exposed columns, vertical bands of windows, and stone panels. Sited perpendicular to Massachusetts Avenue, it would have created a wall at the edge of an open plaza on which stood the auditorium and chapel, functioning as an orthogonal foil to their sculptural forms. It was also positioned to reinforce an axis terminating in Bosworth's temple-fronted building complex. The plaza was intended to be surfaced in triangles of grass and paving and to serve as the roof of a below-grade parking garage. MIT administration rejected the plaza and garage in favor of a lawn.
    Job numbers for projects at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology overlap, since all three of the projects (one of which was unrealized) are located on the same site. Job 5007 generally refers to the Kresge Auditorium, 5303 to the Chapel, and 6007 to the Student Union. Photographs of the two completed structures are listed together below as Jobs 5007 and 5303.
    - Drawings
      - Architectural, undated (Box 165)
      - Electrical and mechanical prints, undated (Box 166)
      - Site, bulletins, details, undated (Box 167)
        - Additional material (Box 677, Folder 107)
  - Jobs 5007 and 5303: Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, MA: Kresge Auditorium and Chapel
    - Advertisement for Holtkamp Organs featuring Auditorium interior, 1956 (Box 163, Folder 487)
    - Clippings, 1953-1957 (Box 163, Folder 490 - 491)
      - Additional material (Box 671, Folder 12)
    - Clippings, 1956-1989, undated (Box 168, Folder 492 - 494)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1955-1962 (Box 168, Folder 495 - 496)
    - Dedication brochure and alumni fund report, 1955 (Box 168, Folder 495)
    - Drawings
      - Typical elevation, plan [showing line of vertical window plane]; bulletins; floor plans; site plan, phase II, Circa 1955-1956 (Box 677, Folder 107)
    - Photographs
      - Early auditorium and chapel renderings, undated (Box 168, Folder 496)
      - Exhibition photos and text, undated (Box 168, Folder 497)
      - Existing site conditions, undated (Box 168, Folder 498)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 168, Folder 499)
      - Intermediate auditorium and chapel site plan, undated (Box 168, Folder 500)
      - Model, 1955, undated (Box 168, Folder 501)
      - Negatives and transparencies, 1953-1955, undated (Box 168, Folder 502)
    - Photographs of auditorium
      - Construction, 1953-1954 (Box 168, Folder 503)
        - Additional material (Folder 692A)
      - Exteriors, 1955-1963, undated (Box 168, Folder 504)
        - Additional material (Box 675, Folder 80)
      - Floor plans and sections, 1953 (Box 168, Folder 505)
      - Interiors, 1955-1956, undated (Box 169, Folder 506)
      - Model, undated (Box 169, Folder 507)
    - Slides
      - Construction, undated (Box 169, Folder 508)
      - Evening views, undated (Box 169, Folder 509)
      - Exteriors
        - Auditorium, undated (Box 169, Folder 510)
        - Chapel, undated (Box 169, Folder 511)
        - Site, 1962, undated (Box 169, Folder 512)
      - Interiors
        - Auditorium, undated (Box 169, Folder 513)
        - Chapel, undated (Box 169, Folder 514)
      - Models, undated (Box 169, Folder 515)
    - Specifications for auditorium
      - Addenda and bulletins, 1953 (Box 169, Folder 516)
      - General conditions; architectural, undated (Box 169, Folder 517)
      - Mechanical, undated (Box 169, Folder 518)
      - Reroofing, 1961 (Box 169, Folder 519)
  - Job 5101: Brandeis University, Waltham, MA: Women's Dining Hall
    - Drawings
      - Architectural, heating, plumbing, electrical prints, undated (Box 170)
      - Brandeis Housing Project; Residence Hall, undated (Box 171)
      - Master plan and early studies, undated (Box 172)
    - Morris Gordon & Son, Inc. kitchen equipment details, 1953 (Box 169, Folder 520)
    - Specifications
      - Addenda and bulletins, 1952-1953 (Box 169, Folder 521)
      - General construction; plumbing; heating and ventilating; electrical work; refrigeration systems, 1952 (Box 173, Folder 522)
      - Kitchen and cafeteria equipment [including addenda], 1952-1953 (Box 173, Folder 523)
      - Plumbing, heating and ventilating; electrical work; refrigeration systems, undated (Box 173, Folder 524)
  - Job 5102: Yale University, New Haven, CT: Physics Building
    - Brochure: "A New Physics Building at Yale", [1952] (Box 173, Folder 525)
    - Clipping: "Proposed Physics Building for Yale University", Architectural Record, 1953 (Box 173, Folder 526)
    - Photographs
      - Models, undated (Box 173, Folder 527)
      - Renderings, 1951, undated (Box 173, Folder 528)
      - Site plan; building cross-section; floor plans, [1951] (Box 173, Folder 529)
    - Presentation: Perspective renderings [one in color], undated (Folder 692B)
  - Job 5103:Brandeis University, Waltham, MA:Dining Hall and Social Building: Drawings, undated (Box 174)
  - Jobs 5105, 5205, 5301, 6208: University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI: Campus Planning
    The University of Michigan hired Saarinen to serve as design consultant for a new satellite campus occupying a hilly 376-acre farmland site a mile north of its historic campus in Ann Arbor. Eero Saarinen and Associates proposed a series of loosely linked courtyards located on different levels and surrounding an approximately 15-acre centrally situated court known as "the forum," which would be bordered by four buildings, including a library and student union. Saarinen hoped that the new campus would be relatively self-sufficient, with entire colleges complete with student housing, so that only professors would need to commute and there would always be a lively pedestrian presence. As built, the North Campus contains a wide variety of buildings and facilities, not exclusively whole colleges, and does not include the forum. Buildings, all designed by different architects, were constructed as needs and funding were identified.